Ben Bartlett, Ph.D.

Physicist specializing in programmable photonics, quantum information, and optical computation

Summary

I am a physicist with extensive software engineering experience interested in optical computing. I have worked in the intersection of ML and photonics and am fascinated by physical computing systems.

Contact

9 803.238.8594

benjamincbartlett@gmail.com
bencbartlett.com

Google Scholar - Ben Bartletttwitter.com/bencbartlett

Q github.com/bencbartlett

Skills

Programming:

Fluent: Python, Mathematica,
TypeScript, QuTiP,
NumPy/SciPy/Matplotlib, ™TEX
Experienced: PyTorch, TensorFlow,
JavaScript, GLSL, meep
Familiar: C++, C, Julia, rllib, ray
Passable: Haskell, MATLAB, Kotlin

Software:

Blender, Ableton Live, AutoCAD, Autodesk Inventor, Illustrator, Final Cut Pro, ffmpeg, LyX, Sphinx, Doxygen, TypeDoc

Laboratory:

nanofabrication, optical lithography, free-space optics, high-vacuum systems

Mathematical:

quantum physics, electrodynamics, linear algebra, machine learning, complexity theory, general relativity, nonlinear optics, numerical methods

Miscellaneous:

scientific visualization and animation [portfolio], generative art, music production, sound design

Selected honors

2018: Hertz Fellowship Finalist

2015: Jean J. Dixon Fellowship 2012: Davidson Fellows Finalist

2012: CERN research award

2012: 4th in physics, International Science and Engineering Fair

2012: 1st in physics. National JSHS

Education

Stanford University • Ph.D. Applied Physics • 2017 – 2022

- > Dissertation: Photonic computing architectures for classical and quantum information processing [link]
- Advised by Prof. Shanhui Fan; research in optical computing, machine learning, quantum information, nanophotonics, nanofabrication, quantum optics

Stanford University • M.S. Electrical Engineering • 2019 – 2022

Caltech • B.S. Physics + Computer Science • 2013 – 2017

Employment

PsiQuantum • *Quantum computer architect* • Palo Alto, CA • 2022 – present Large-scale simulation of photonic components for a fault-tolerant quantum computer

X Development (Google X) • PhD residency • Mountain View, CA • 2021 – 2022 Undisclosed project involving electromagnetics, machine learning, distributed computing

AT&T Foundry / INQNET • Quantum networks • Palo Alto, CA • 2017

Developed a parallelized quantum network simulator with channel noise models

SLAC National Accelerator Lab • *Engineering intern* • Menlo Park, CA • 2016 Wrote testing system for camera readout boards on the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope

CERN • *Undergraduate researcher* • Geneva, Switzerland • 2015 – 2016

Developed a vertex reconstruction algorithm for the CMS, improving resolution by ~160×

Patents

- > <u>B. Bartlett</u>, A. Dutt, and S. Fan, "A scalable design for a photonic quantum computer using a fiber ring and a single coherently controlled atom", USPTO 63/087,661 (2020)
- > <u>B. Bartlett</u>, A. Dutt, and S. Fan, "Systems and methods for deterministic photonic quantum computing in a synthetic time dimension", WO 2022/076982 A1 (2022) [link]

Selected publications (of 17 total, >580 citations)

- > Pai, et al. "Experimentally realized in situ backpropagation for deep learning in photonic neural networks", *Science*, 380, 398-404 (2023) [link] [press coverage]
- > Bartlett, et al. "Deterministic photonic quantum computation in a synthetic time dimension", *Optica*, 8, 1515-1523 (2021) [link] [press coverage]
- > Bartlett, et al. "Universal programmable photonic architecture for quantum information processing", *Physical Review A*, 101, 042319 (2020) [link]
- > Fard, et al. "Experimental realization of arbitrary activation functions for optical neural networks", *Optics Express*, 28, 12138-12148 (2020) [link]
- > Pai, Bartlett, et al. "Matrix optimization on universal unitary photonic devices", *Physical Review Applied*, 11, 064044 (2019) [link]
- > Williamson, et al. "Reprogrammable Electro-Optic Nonlinear Activation Functions for Optical Neural Networks" [Invited], IEEE JSTQE, 26 (1), 1-12 (2019) [link]

Open-source software contributions (* lead developer)

- > neuroptica* (★ 182 ¥ 39): a flexible simulation package for optical neural networks
- > SOUANCH* (★ 42 ¥ 10): distributed simulation framework for quantum networks
- \rightarrow QuTiP (\star 1.5k % 630): the Quantum Toolbox in Python
- > meep (★ 993 🖁 543): popular open-source electromagnetics simulation package
- > <u>3D-printed-mirror-array</u>* (★ 2.4k ¥ 143): generates custom 3D-printable hexagonal mirror arrays capable of reflecting sunlight into arbitrary patterns
- > Overmind* (★ 497 🖁 146): a multi-agent bot for a competitive online strategy game
- \rightarrow <u>ising-compiler</u>* (\star 49 % 2): compiles Boolean circuits into adiabatically cooled spins
- > neural-maxwell* (★ 54 ¥ 20): ML model for computing electromagnetic field solutions
- → <u>qpga</u>* (★ 98 ¥ 18): TensorFlow-based simulations of photonic programmable gate arrays
- > psiblend*: library for visualizing photonic circuits in Blender, used at PsiQuantum